A Guide to the Records of the Office of the Vice-President, Walter S. Newman, 1946-1947
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Office of the Vice-President Records, Walter S. Newman, 1946-1947
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Newman, Walter S. (Walter Stephenson), 1895-1978
RG 03/01
1.6 Cubic Feet 2 boxes
Walter Stephenson Newman (1895-1978) was the first individual to hold the office of Vice-President at Virginia Tech. His tenure began 15 May 1946 but only lasted until 1 September 1947, when he became the tenth president of Virginia Tech, serving from 1947 to 1962. This small collection consists of correspondence concerning curriculum revisions, letters from and replies to other colleges on various matters, and copies of memoranda to faculty and department heads.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The records were transferred to Special Collections prior to 2016.
Biographical Note
Walter Stephenson Newman (1895-1978) was the first individual to hold the office of Vice-President at Virginia Tech. His tenure began 15 May 1946 but only lasted until 1 September 1947, when he became the tenth president of Virginia Tech, serving from 1947 to 1962. As president, Newman conferred more degrees than all his predecessors combined and oversaw more than $20,000,000 in campus construction. Newman put greater emphasis on research and graduate programs than any previous president, and several new graduate degree programs were established while he was president. In 1953, the first black student was admitted to Virginia Tech, notwithstanding Newman's active opposition to integration. Also during Newman's term, the status of the Corps of Cadets was studied, then strengthened with the appointment of the first full-time commandant of cadets since World War I.
Walter Newman was born in Woodstock, Virginia, on July 20, 1895. He earned an undergraduate degree from Hampden-Sydney College in 1917, a Masters of Science in agriculture from Virginia Tech in 1919, and a Ph.D. Degree in agriculture from Penn State in 1931. He was Assistant Professor of Agricultural Education at Virginia Tech from 1922 to 1936, when he became Assistant Superintendent of Public Instruction for the state of Virginia. He also served as state administrator of the National Youth Administration from 1936 to 1942.
Newman returned to Virginia Tech as Vice-President in May 1946. He assumed many of the duties of the office of the president in December 1946, when President John Hutcheson was hospitalized. The Board of Visitors appointed Newman Acting President in May 1947 and President on September 1, 1947.
Newman's presidency saw "the beginning of a strong effort to strengthen the offerings in the humanities," Duncan Lyle Kinnear writes in A Short History of Virginia Tech. Courses in Russian, philosophy and ethics were introduced, and the Department of Philosophy and Religion was organized in 1955.
Masters programs were added in City and Regional Planning, Engineering Geology, Aeronautical Engineering, Nuclear Engineering Physics, and Mathematics, and doctoral programs in Applied Mechanics and Geology, Mathematics, Aeronautical Engineering, and Civil Engineering. The Departments of Forestry and Wildlife Conservation, Veterinary Science, and Entomology were created from the Department of Biology; the Department of Extension Education was begun in the School of Agriculture; and the School of Home Economics was created. Roanoke Technical Institute, a division of Tech's School of Engineering, opened its doors in 1961.
In 1957, the university acquired a wind tunnel for use in its aeronautical engineering program. A nuclear reactor simulator, the first in the country owned by a college, began operations in 1957.
Dormitory capacity increased from 1,976 to 3,904 between 1947 and 1962. Buildings constructed while Newman was president include Newman Library (1955), Femoyer, Thomas, and Monteith dormitories (1949), Smyth and Henderson Halls (1950), the first wing of Randolph Hall and Williams Hall (1953), Commerce Hall (now Pamplin Hall, 1957), and Memorial Chapel (1960), and construction was begun on Cassell Coliseum and Schultz Dining Hall, and Vawter and Barringer dormitories (1962).
The Virginia Polytechnic Institute Educational Foundation, Inc., was established by the Board of Visitors in 1948 to increase gifts and endowments, and a Director of Development was hired in 1958. The Virginia Polytechnic Institute-Blacksburg-Christiansburg Water Authority was organized in 1954-1955, ensuring the campus with an abundant supply of water on campus beginning in 1957.
President Newman suffered a heart attack in March 1961. He returned to work in July but presented the Board of Visitors with his formal resignation soon afterward. Newman's resignation was made official December 4, 1961.
Jenkins Middell Robertson, compiler and editor. Historical Data Book, Centennial Edition(Blacksburg, VA: Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, 1964 and 1972), 21-24; Duncan Lyle Kinnear, The First 100 Years: A History of Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University(Blacksburg, VA: Virginia Polytechnic Institute Educational Foundation, Inc., 1972), 357-413; Peter Wallenstein, "The First Black Students at Virginia Tech," Diversity News, Vol. 4, No. 1 (Fall 1997), 3.
Scope and Content
The Records of the Office of the Vice-President, Walter S. Newman, 1946-1947, comprises correspondence concerning curriculum revisions, letters from and replies to other colleges on various matters, and copies of memoranda to faculty and department heads. The collection is organized alphabetically by department, individual's name, or subject.
Arrangement
This collection is organized alphabetically.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Materials
Records of the Office of the President, Walter S. Newman, 1947-1962 (Bulk 1947-1961), RG 2/10. Finding aid available online.
Walter S. Newman Collection, 1930-1968, n.d., Ms2015-006. Finding aid available online.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Virginia Polytechnic Institute; Faculty; University Archives; University History
Genre and Form Terms:
Correspondence
Persons:
Newman, Walter S. (Walter Stephenson), 1895-1978
Contents List
- Admissions office CDR. Farrier, Mr. Morris, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Agriculture Curriculum Committee, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Alumni Association, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Anticipated Personnel Needs, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Arlington Branch Extension, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Association of Land Grant Colleges and Universities, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Board of Visitors Report of President, etc, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Business Administration and Academic Science Curriculum Committee, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Cassell, S.K. Business Manager, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Central Steering Committee, on and off campus college training for veterans and nonveterans, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Classroom and Laboratory Facilities Study, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Committee on Matter of students taking final Examinations, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Cregger, S.G. - Auditor, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Cultural and Social Progress Committee, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Curriculum Committees, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Curriculum Revision at V.P.I., 1946 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Danville Extension Branch, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Dietrick, L.B. Director | Extension Division, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Dunlevy, D.B. Guidance and Counseling, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Educational policy and program committee, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Engineering Curriculum Committee, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Enrollment, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Executive Bulletins, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Faculty, General, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Federal works Agency, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Foreign Students Committee, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Graduate Studies Louis O'Shaughnessy, Director, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Honor System, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Hutcheson, John R. President, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Hutcheson, T.B. Dean of Agriculture, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Inquiries from other Colleges, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Leave Policy, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Legislation - Miscellaneous, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Library Ralph M. Brown, Librarian, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Miles, C.P. Dean of the College, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Miller, G. Tyler State Supt. Of Public Instruction, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Mimeographs, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Munford, T.W. Commandant of Cadets Part 1., 1946 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Munford, T.W. Commandant of Cadets Part 2., 1946 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Norfolk Extension Branch St. Helena Extension, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Norris, E.B. Dean of Engineering, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Personal Needs Survey Forms, 1946-07-09 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Placement Office, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Radford College, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Radford Ordinance Works, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Registration Procedure, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Requests for Personnel, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Richmond Branch Extension, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Salary Scales (survey), 1946 (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Sanders H.W. Dept. of Vocational Education, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 50)
- Scholarships, fellowships, Loans ( Newman, Cassell, Miles ), 1946 (Box 1, Folder 51)
- State Board of Education Memos, etc., 1946 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- State Board of Education - Reports, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- State Department of Education (Material Dr. Newman Brought with him May 1946), 1946-05 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Student Affairs, Director of, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Student Life Committee, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Student Senate, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Teaching Manual (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Veterans' Administration, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Virginia Academy of Science, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- V.P.I. Research Foundation, Inc., 1946 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- War Assets Administration (surplus chemicals), 1946 (Box 2, Folder 11)